COMMENTATOR 1:...and Bannister has done it.
旁述1：班尼斯特成功啦！
Now, he's out on his feet. His coach and team manager tell him.
现在，他的教练和领队叫他甩开腿冲。
1954年，罗杰·班尼斯特成为首位一英里跑进4分钟内的人类
he's achieved his ambition, a mile in three minutes 59.4 seconds.
他实现了夙愿，3分59.4秒跑完1英里。（译者注：1954年）
COMMENTATOR 2: Jimmy Hines is going to win the race!
旁述2: 吉米海恩斯马上就拿下比赛！
1968年，吉姆·海恩斯成为首位一百米跑进10秒内的人类
Jim Hines is the winner! Lennox Miller, second, Charlie Greene,third.
吉米海恩斯冠军、伦诺克斯米勒第二、查理格兰特第三。
Jim Hines is the world's fastest human.
吉米海恩斯是世界上跑得最快的人！
到了20世纪末，人们大胆猜想，下一个里程碑即将到来
COMMENTATOR 3: He breaks the world record by an astonishing margin,
旁述3: 他的成绩大幅度打破世界记录！
one minute and 17 seconds.
提升了1分17秒。
And history has been made in Berlin in astonishing style.
用令人震惊的方式在柏林书写了历史。
马拉松跑进2小时内
CAPCOM: You are go for landing. Over.
登月舱通讯员：准备降落，报告完毕。
BUZZ ALDRIN: Roger. Understand. Go for landing. 3,000 feet.
BUZZ ALDRIN：收到，明白。开始降落，3000英尺。
CAPCOM: Altitude, 1600. 1400 feet, still looking very good.
登月舱通讯员：高度1600，1400英尺，目前状况很好。
ALDRIN: We're go.
ALDRIN：准备着陆。
We're go.
准备着陆。
Contact light.
着陆灯打开。
OK, engine stop.
好，关停发动机。
CAPCOM: We copy you down, Eagle.
登月舱通讯员：着陆信号收到了，雄鹰号。
NEIL ARMSTRONG: It's one small step for man,
尼尔阿姆斯特朗：这是个人的一小步，
one giant leap for mankind.
却是人类的一大步。
跑柏林马拉松和跑维也纳是两件不同的事情
柏林马拉松是参赛，然后打破世界纪录
维也纳是“破二”，是创造历史
就像第一个登上月球的人类
REPORTER: Welcome to a foggy morning here in Vienna, Austria,
记者：我们迎来一个大雾的早上，这里是奥地利维也纳。
where one man will attempt to go where no man has been before.
有个人将尝试挑战从来没有人做到的事情。
Pushing his body and mind to the limit
把身体和意志都推到极限。
with the aid of scientific research and meticulous preparation,
在科研和一丝不苟备战的帮助下，
Kenya's Eliud Kipchoge will hope to run 26.2 miles in under two hours
肯尼亚的埃鲁德·基普乔格希望在两小时跑完26.2英里的马拉松距离。
and, in doing so, beat one of the great sporting barriers of our time.
一旦达成，就将打破我们这个时代最大的运动壁垒之一。
Kipchoge! Kipchoge! Kipchoge! Kipchoge!
基普乔格！基普乔格！基普乔格！基普乔格！
环球影业 及 雷德利斯科特创意集团呈献
RAS电影出品
制片人 Ross Plummer
肯尼亚 里夫特山区
人生，总是有着一些起起落落
跑马拉松，也会遇到很多挑战
有起有落
训练带来的痛苦
奔跑时的痛苦
以及冲线时的喜悦
要我说，马拉松就像是人生一般。
你怎么看待痛苦，你的人生就会怎么过
在这个世界，你需要捱过苦痛才能获得成功
Kalenjin 著名的肯尼亚长跑之乡，迪卡侬的跑步系列产品就以Kalenji命名
我是Kalenjin人，我们相信，人生下来是需要磨砺的
随着日渐成长，人人都教我们如何抗拒痛苦
而在翻过了苦痛之巅，就能找到成功
2016里约奥运会 马拉松冠军奖牌
2016伦敦马拉松 冠军奖牌
2015伦敦马拉松 冠军奖牌
2014鹿特丹马拉松 冠军奖牌
我年幼时，母亲对我十分严厉
她是一名幼儿园老师，
她总想让大家听话，守规矩，她说什么我们就做什么
但当我进入了体育行业
我明白了自律
才是驱使我前进的动力
母亲独自把我养大
她和父亲结了婚，但是父亲在我出生前过世了
我未曾见过我父亲
那时候我的日子不好过
你也知道，这个社会总是轻视没有爸爸的孩子
一般来说
单亲母亲带大的孩子，总被人看不起
总听老人说，这样的人不是当领袖人物的料子
但我心想，我应该更要加把劲
这样才能减轻我的兄弟姐妹和母亲的负担
我自己是不相信人有极限的
当你心里想着“我做不到”
奇迹就不会出现
COMMENTATOR: Hicham El Guerrouj coming home,
解说员：Hicham El Guerrouj快到终点了！
Eliud Kipchoge, Kenenisa Bekele.
埃鲁德·基普乔格，肯尼萨·贝克勒
Kipchoge in the red. Can he get to the finals Yes!
身穿红衣的是基普乔格，他能赢得冠军吗？他成功了！
（2003年世锦赛男子5000米冠军）
Kipchoge edging out Hicham El Guerrouj!
基普乔格以微弱优势战胜了Hicham El Guerrouj。
COMMENTATOR 2: Eighteen years of age. Eliud Kipchoge.
解说员2：埃鲁德·基普乔格，才18岁。
You know, you hear about child prodigies that can play the piano.
就是，你听说过会弹钢琴的神童吧，
How can you do this at 18, when you should be a senior in high school
别人18岁正在读高中的时候，他就赢得冠军了
我的人生哲学，差不多就像是
当你要往树上爬
就应该是从这根树枝爬到下一根
此刻你爬上了一根树枝，站稳了
准备爬下一根树枝的时候，先试试它够不够稳
然后再爬上去
我跑过的所有马拉松，就是一场人生体验
我打破了马拉松世界纪录，赢过奥运会金牌
但更美好的事情还在前面呢
所以我现在十分渴望（马拉松）跑进2小时内
NDUHIU: You know, science has it that the first man to run 42K
Nduhiu（Kipchoge的物理治疗师）：有研究推断第一个不用两小时就能
below two hours,
跑完42公里的人
will do it in about 2075.
要到2075年才出现。
That is 50 years from now. He wants to do it now.
那就是50年后啊。而他现在就想跑进两小时。
从未有人真的想过要跑进2小时内
从未有人敢想象人类真的能做得到（跑进2小时内）
我从心里准备好了要去尝试
我也相信我能做到
His mind is... [EXHALES SHARPLY] It's something you can't describe.
他的想法...真是难以形容
Berlin, 2015,
柏林马拉松，2015年
he is running at kilometer-five and the insoles are flapping out.
他跑到5公里处，鞋垫就滑出来了。
And you're saying...this guy will drop from this
你可能会说，这家伙要退赛了吧，
because it will cause blisters.
因为（鞋垫这样硌脚）会磨出水泡。
But he went on, and actually set his personal best.
但他坚持下去了，实际上还创造了个人最好成绩（PB）。
So you look at him and you say, "OK, this is magical."
所以你看着他，会惊叹：“哇，这太神奇了。”
Because you were seeing somebody here with a mind that,
因为你眼前的这个人，他的想法是如此的坚定，
if he puts it on something, nothing will distract him from it.
如果他专注于做某件事，那就没别的东西可以让他分神了。
He will go for it.
他会全力以赴完成的。
COMMENTATOR: Kipchoge puts his foot down.
解说员：基普乔格开足马力。
The London Marathon belongs to Eliud Kipchoge.
（2015年）伦敦马拉松的冠军属于埃鲁德·基普乔格。
Eliud Kipchoge.
埃鲁德·基普乔格（2016年里约奥运会马拉松冠军）
Eliud Kipchoge, arguably the greatest ever.
埃鲁德·基普乔格，可以说是有史以来最伟大（的马拉松运动员）
（2014年芝加哥马拉松冠军）（2016年伦敦马拉松冠军）
This will be the first sub 2:02 clocking,
这将是人类首个跑进2小时2分的记录，（2018年柏林马拉松冠军）
and by a monstrous margin, he is going to break the world record.
并且会以惊人的幅度打破世界纪录。
Particularly in marathon running, he is the greatest ever, by a long way.
特别是在马拉松运动里，他是有史以来最伟大的运动员，无人能及。
The quickest. A man who knows how to win.
他是最快的人，一个知道如何取胜的人。（2019伦敦马拉松冠军）
启蒙我跑步的人
是我同村的邻居，也就是我的教练，Patrick Sang
COMMENTATOR: Sang is second. One, two, three for Kenya.
解说员：桑第二。肯尼亚人囊括1、2、3名。
我看着他奔跑，暗暗发誓我要像他那样
然后当我开始练跑步，我就请他来训练我了
SANG: I was a fortunate guy
桑：我是个幸运儿。
to have had help from so many people throughout my childhood years.
从童年起就一直得到许多人的帮助。
All the way to being a runner.
一路成为一名跑步运动员。
So, when I came back, one of the things that I wanted to do
所以，当我回到国内，我首先想去做的事是
was to give back to the community.
回馈社会。（Patrick Sang，基普乔格的教练）
So I was actively involved in helping young athletes in this country.
我一直在积极帮助我国的年轻运动员成长
Somehow Eliud knew that I was in this position,
然后Eliud知道我在这里做教练，
and he came to me like any other youngster
他像其他年轻运动员那样来找我
asking for a training plan.
想要一份训练计划。
I would give him a training plan for two weeks,
我给他一份两周的训练计划
and he would come, religiously, every two weeks,
然后他就十分认真地，每隔两周来找我
to ask for more.
想学更多。
But at one point he told me,
然后某一天，他跟我说，
"I've made the regional team to go to the Nationals.
“我已经从地区队升到国家队了”
I want to be guided."
“我想拜您为师。”
He also told me that he took up running because he used to see me run
他还告诉我，他之所以开始跑步，就是因为曾经看过我跑步
at the high school, and said why don't I try, like this guy
那时他还在高中，还说过“为什么我不试试，像这个人一样（做个跑步运动员）”？
And that's why he was coming to me for advice.
这就是他来找我寻求建议的原因。
So that was the beginning.
这一切就这么开始了。
COMMENTATOR: He breaks the world record
解说员：他打破纪录啦，
by an astonishing margin.
巨大的优势。
One minute and 17 seconds. Patrick Sang, his coach, his companion
1分17秒，帕特里克·桑，他的教练、他的亲密战友。
for run after run, race after race, year after year.
年复一年，一次又一次的奔跑，一场又一场的比赛。
SANG: It's just pure trust.
桑：只是纯粹的信任。
He never asks what are we going to do next week, next month, tomorrow.
他从来不问明天练什么，下周呢，下个月呢？
And I think, without trust, you cannot go far in this business.
而我认为，没有信任的话，这事儿对谁都不能长久。
All of us in life, we go through different phases.
我们每个人在生命中都会经历不同的阶段。
And any situation gives you lessons.
任何情况都会有教训。
And it depends on how you interact with that background.
这取决于你在当时怎么做。
Some will take it positively, and use it positively.
有的人会积极看待，积极对待。
You know, there have been so many theories
你知道的，有很多理论
why we have this rich pool of talent.
为什么我们有这么丰富的人才储备，
I believe strongly in the theory of Darwin,
我坚信达尔文的理论
the survival of the fittest.
适者生存。
Most of our athletes come from humble backgrounds.
我们大多数运动员出身卑微
You have to fight, you have to be strong.
你必须努力抗争，你必须坚强起来
And I think in Kenya,
我认为在肯尼亚
the strictures that were laid down by the colonial government
过去殖民政府给制定了诸多规则
to compete for the Empire in the Empire Games
好让殖民地运动员为宗主国出力
meant a tradition was formed under that unfriendly regime.
这就意味着许多传统在各种不友好的政权影响下演变
And I think over time they were perfected.
（训练、比赛里的）一些传统是在这样一种不好的制度下形成的
COMMENTATOR: Keino making this crowd roar.
评述：Keino让观众欢呼雀跃
He is now 15 yards clear.
他现在领先第二名15码
When you pass a place, you leave some dust in your wake.
当你经过一个地方必定会在身后留下尘埃
And some dust can throw in something glittering.
而这些尘埃当中可能会留下一些闪光点
I think that would be something that glitters
我想这些闪光点会在
out of the unfriendly dust that we experienced as a country.
我们曾经历过的那段黑暗历史中熠熠生辉
MAN: The people here in Kenya, masses of the Africans here in Kenya,
男性旁白：这些肯尼亚的非洲人，人数众多
are probably roughly at about the same stage
他们所处的落后境况
Great Britain was 500 years ago.
估计跟大英帝国500年前的境况差不多
We do not think that the normal forms of democracy are suitable.
我们觉得常规的民主制度不适合这里
COMMENTATOR: Simpson in second place. O'Brien is third.
评述：现在第二位是SIMPSON，O'BRIEN位列第三
Wilkinson is fourth, and surely no one will catch the African.
Wilkinson第四，看样子没人追得上那个非洲选手
SANG: People heard through the radio
桑：人们从电台节目中听到
that there was this great guy who could run so fast,
曾经有一个跑的飞快的选手
and his name was Kip Keino.
他的名字叫 KIP KEINO
COMMENTATOR: And Keino is going faster,
评述：KEINO又加速了！
and Simpson is going harder, too.
Simpson也在奋力追赶
SANG: He was a household name.
桑：他曾经家喻户晓
There were songs sung about him.
还有一首歌歌颂他
When we were kids, we used to say, "Run like Kip Keino!"
我们小时候常说：“我们要像KIP KEINO那样跑步”！
You get one person from an area running very well,
如果某个地方出现了一个跑步非常厉害的人物
then he becomes a mentor to many others. There is an example to follow.
他就会成为大家的导师、众人效仿的榜样
But then, there is dominance on the Kalenjin group,
不久后，KALENJIN（译注：肯尼亚地名，以盛产长跑高手著称）
的队伍就出现了一位有统治能力的队友
particularly where long-distance running is concerned.
尤其是长距离跑项目
Every single time Eliud laces his shoes and takes the guys out for a run,
每次当Eliud（基普乔格的名）穿上跑鞋，带上队员出去训练的时候
he doesn't have to say anything.
他什么都不用说
If you're in that camp, all you have to do is see in his eyes.
如果你在那个训练营训练，你要做的就是看着他的眼睛
You know, his dedication
他眼神透露出的那种全力以赴的决心
and his will to just keep pushing every single time.
和意志就会推动你每一次不断前进
NDUHIU: For you to succeed in the majority of these things,
NDUHIU:如果你们想赢得这一切
you have got to get a team that believes in your dream.
你一定要找到一个，和你有共同梦想的团队
You are the vision carrier.
你是传递信念的人
But the cast that supports you have also to believe
但背后的团队需要有同样坚定的信念
and commit to the dream.
我们才能把梦想变成现实。
CHUMO: Eliud is super consistent in whatever he does.
CHUMO: Eliud都能贯彻始终（是一个长期主义者）
It's all about discipline.
这全都归结于他的自律
It's a storm of conditions that come together to make this man who he is.
所有的一切造就了他
BRAILSFORD: He's got an incredible physiology.
BRAILSFORD: 他的生理条件得天独厚
He's got incredible efficiency as an athlete.
作为一名运动员，他有着难以置信的动作效率
And he's got an absolutely incredible mind. I mean, an incredible mind.
更为重要的是他的心志，他的心志之强大无出其右
COE: He is the perfect shape.
COE: 他的体型就是专门为跑步打造
He has almost perfect posture.
跑姿几乎可以说完美
He puts his feet down...and it's a dream.
他的脚步之轻盈
He almost floats.
就好像在梦境中飘浮
Athletics is an individual sport and Eliud is able
田径本来是一项个人运动，Eliud能够把
to make an individual sport a kind of team sport
这项个人运动变成为某种意义上的团队运动。
with the way he does things in camp.
而且他从来都是以身作则
He feels it's a way of inspiring people. That is something which I see in Eliud
因为他认为这样才能够真正激励队友
that you don't see in almost any other athlete.
这是我在其他多数运动员身上看不到的特质
KAPTAGAT 训练营 肯尼亚
SANG: Running is a taxing exercise.
桑：跑步是一项极其既耗心神，又费体力的运动
It takes a lot of energy from the system.
身体为此需要调用大量的能量
The set-up we have in Kaptagat
我们在KAPTAGAT建立的体系对于跑者来说
is an ideal environment where somebody
是一个十分理想的环境
can have around them the right people to give them moral support.
因为在这里，你身边都是志同道合的人，给予你强大的精神支持
CHOGE: Eliud has really helped young people, and some of us
CHOGE：Eliud给予队友，给予年轻人很多帮助
because what you see from him makes you believe
因为他的经历让你相信
that if this person can do this, also I can do that.
他能做到的，我也一样可以做到
He is a mentor to so many young athletes.
他是许多年轻运动员的导师
Squat! Get into the squatting position.
深蹲！现在准备练深蹲了！
TRAINER: Open. Close.
教练：迈腿，收腿
Two. Close.
再来一次，收腿
Three. Close. Four. Close.
三次，收腿。四次，收腿。
就我个人而言， 我不想当领军人物， 但是我想引导大家
所以我希望让大家跟着我迈向成功
同时大家也能在适当的时候做适当的事情
NJOROGE: People look up to him
NJOROGE：人们敬仰他
because he's not trying to be something else.
因为他别无所求
He's completely sincere.
就是真诚地对待一切
MAN: The camp is a really special place.
路人甲：训练营是一个非常特别的所在
The athletes organize everything in camp themselves.
所有的运动员对营中大小事务亲力亲为
NJOROGE: It is very austere.
NJOROGE: 这里的生活很简朴
But I think you then get connected with what really matters.
也正因此你会把注意力放在真正重要的事情上
You can get with very little. All the other things are fluff.
你不会被太多事情分心，世俗的欲望都是浮云
CHOGE: There are so many things that I've learned from him.
CHOGE:我在他身上学到很多
One of them is really... be humble.
其中最重要的就是...谦逊
No matter what success you achieve in your life, always be humble.
不管你在人生中获得多大的成就，都要切记保持谦逊
In his case, humility is something that's absolutely core.
在他身上，谦逊的品质是从内而外散发的
He doesn't even think about it.
他甚至都没有想过自己是这样的人
It's a natural thing that emanates out from him, really.
好像这个品质是与生俱来的一样
It's central to the way that he operates.
决定了他的行事准则
有人告诉我
你要想要过一个丰盛的人生，就要做一个谦逊的人
是的，我想要过一个安乐、简单
和平凡的人生
我不想走到哪都引人瞩目
我只想和其他人融洽相处
我想和大家自由自在地互相交流
CHUMO: This is the best training area for running.
CHUMO: 这里是世界上最好的跑步训练基地
Elite athletes.
为那些
For that person who is aspiring to be the best.
立志成为顶尖选手的精英运动员们打造
AUGUSTINE: We believe in our fitness, we believe in the team
AUGUSTINE: 我们对自己的能力和团队都充满信心
that we have selected to help Eliud.
相信我们可以帮助Eliud实现他的目标
We believe in the coaching that's been provided for us.
我们对教练的指导也充满信心
So we have a strong team.
所以你看我们现在就是一个强大的团队
We do half squat.
我们做半蹲
CHUMO: At the end of the day, all you can do is just
CHUMO: 每一天你要做的就是
train, eat, rest, and repeat.
训练、吃饭、休息然后不断重复
NDUHIU: High-altitude training does them a lot of good.
Nduhiu: 高海拔训练为身体带来很多好处
You develop a higher red blood cell count
可以增加你血液中运输氧气的
that transports the oxygen.
红细胞总量
So when you go and run now at sea level, you find you have an Advantage
所以当你回到平原跑步的时候会变得更有优势
because you're able to carry the oxygen through
因为和他人相比，
much easier than the other person.
你身体的运氧能力更强
NOBLE: An elite athlete will be used to having to capture the oxygen very well.
一个精英运动员的携氧能力应该足够强大
Their genomes are crafted by the evolutionary process
演化的进程造就了他们的基因组
to produce the proteins necessary to capture the oxygen easily,
使其能生产出更多易于携带氧气的血红蛋白
because the oxygen is thin.
因为氧气太稀薄
But it can't be just that.
不仅于此
The elite performers in Kenya are also inheriting the right epigenome.
肯尼亚精英运动员同样继承了合适的表观基因组
That is, the ability to maintain those controls
那就是对身体持续的控制能力
over, not only your muscles, but also the rest of the body.
不仅是肌肉，也包括身体的其他部分
How we behave, the lifestyle, the training,
我们的行为习惯、生活方式和训练方式
the ways in which the body tells the genome what to do
都是我们的身体告诉基因要做什么的方式
I've been fascinated throughout my career
在我的职业生涯中，我一直着迷于探索
by why certain ethnic groups have excelled in sport.
为什么有些种族在运动方面表现优异
If you asked me in 2000, I would have said it's genetic.
如果你在2000年问我，我会回答你那是因为基因遗传
But 20 years later, it's very clear to me,
但20年后，我认为这不仅仅是基因，我们所看到的种种，
and it's actually well accepted now
都是社会经济文化现象，
that what we're observing is a socio-economic cultural phenomenon.
而且社会也广泛认同这个观点了
The very best, or the very, very unique individuals,
对于那些非常拔尖或者非常独特的个体
where genetics plays a massive role
遗传起到了非常重大的作用
but genes alone will not produce success.
但是他们的成功并非仅靠基因优势
You need that right environment.
你还需要一个良好的环境
我认为肯尼亚人之所以
能在运动项目，特别是在田径运动上称王
是因为他们把体育运动当作职业来看待
因为从事体育运动可以养家糊口
他们并不是把跑步当作娱乐休闲的嗜好
COE: You close your eyes and you think about Kenya.
闭上眼睛，想想肯尼亚
You think about athletes,
去想想那里的运动员
and you think about extraordinary performances.
然后再想想他们非凡的运动能力
And there is an ambition, an aspiration, amongst young Kenyan Kids
你可以看到肯尼亚年轻人身上雄心勃勃的斗志
to want to be great runners.
想要成为一名伟大的长跑运动员
When we came out of colonial administration,
当我们摆脱了殖民者的统治
we became independent.
我们独立了
And our first experience as a country in international Competitions
而我们初次作为一个独立的国家参加国际比赛就获得奖牌
was so positive because we won medals from the word go.
这令我们备受鼓舞
And that, in itself, set a tradition that every young athlete coming up
这在后来的每一个运动员中就形成了一个传统，
has a bar that is already set. And that bar is that
他们会有一个既定的标准，而这个标准就是
if you come with anything less than a gold, you are not good.
不夺金，不优秀
The Kenyans train to be the best.
每一位肯尼亚的运动员都把最优秀作为自己的训练目标
And that's, like, a mindset that is very strong for them.
对他们来说，这种心态深深的根植于他们的精神中
无论你是什么肤色，来自哪个国家，大家都很刻苦训练
NDUHIU: Amongst all the Kalenjin group that are running,
Nduhiu: 在所有从事跑步运动的Kalenjin人中
there are those that can have a very low pain threshold.
有一部分人的疼痛阈值非常低
That problem that would actually make another athlete drop,
这个问题真的会令运动员放弃比赛，
Eliud would finish with it.
但Eliud会忍受疼痛完成比赛
His body is exceptional,
他的身体很特别
because he is able to block
因为他能主动忽略
that disruption, that irritation that the pain is causing,
由疼痛造成的分心和干扰
and put it at the back of his mind until the race is over.
将痛苦抛之脑后，直到完成比赛
NDUHIU: Actually, his biggest asset, his mind,
事实上，是他最宝贵的财富，他的意志，
carries him through those very trying moments.
助他度过那些艰苦拼搏的时刻
CHOGE: He is very strong mentally.
CHOGE: 他的内心很强大
He has really developed a way of overcoming the pain.
他已经开发出一种克服疼痛的方法
He always smiles, he always concentrates,
永远面带微笑，永远全神贯注
he always keeps focus on what he does.
他一直专注于当下在做的事，
And I've tried and it really works.
我也尝试了同样的办法，非常有效
You smile a bit, and you forget about the pain and just keep moving.
笑一笑，忘记疼痛，继续前行
NOBLE: When you're exercising,
NOBLE：当你运动时
and you're competing at a very high level,
当你在高水平竞争时
you are doing much more than just running.
你所做的远不止奔跑
You are also putting yourself into a state of mind in which you can do it.
你也将自己置入一种“你可以”的精神状态，
It's a meditative state.
那是种冥想状态。
NDUHIU: You have to align the mind and the whole body,
Nduhiu: 你必须将心与身合一
so that when you tell it to move, it moves as you direct.
这样你向身体发出指令时，才会身随意动。
If you have a disconnect between those two things,
如果你的身心不能合一
that's when you start losing the momentum,
那身体就会失去动力
and it becomes a nightmare for you to sustain.
而这会变成你要面临的噩梦。
COMMENTATOR: We are here at the Autodromo Nazionale Monza
解说员：我们来到了（意大利）蒙扎国家赛车场，
to see if we can really break this barrier.
见证人类突破（2小时）这一关
This is something that has been in the making for two years.
为此我们已经做了两年准备。
TROUW: Breaking the two hours is incredible pressure.
Trouw: 突破两小时的压力大得难以想象
He experienced that for the first time in Monza.
埃鲁德第一次在蒙扎赛道尝试突破这个关口。
That kind of pressure which is different than going for Olympics
这种压力和备战奥运、
or for London Marathon or anything else.
或者伦敦马拉松、或者其他任何事都不同。
And I think in Monza, he was learning to handle it.
而我认为，他正在蒙扎赛道学着去应对。
It was really hard for him to convince himself
他要花很多功夫
that he was going to run under two hours.
才能说服自己“我可以跑进2小时”。
It took him six, seven months to prepare physically,
他花了六七个月在体能上，
but mainly, mentally, to be ready on the starting line
更主要的是在心理上，才做好了踏上起跑线的准备，
that he had really internalized that he was going to achieve it.
并从心底里相信自己必将成功。
At that time he came from a personal best of 2:03:05.
当时他的个人最佳记录为2小时零3分零5秒
So he had to prepare his mind
因此他必须做好心理建设
to go three minutes faster than he had ever had done in his life.
——比他人生中最快的一次还要快3分钟
COMMENTATOR: Believe me, that's not just a first place,
解说员：相信我，那将不仅仅是他成为第一个（跑进2小时内），
that is a moment of marathon history.
那更是马拉松历史上的重要一刻。
HERMENS: At Monza, it was very clear it was a very big step.
Hermens: 很明显，在蒙扎迈出的是人类历史的一大步
I remember going to the racecourse at Monza
我记得我在去蒙扎赛道的路上
and thinking to myself, "Three minutes. That's a lot!"
我在想：三分钟啊！这差距好大！
COMMENTATOR: Thirty seconds.
解说员：30秒（后起跑）
Nine, eight, seven, six...
9、8、7、6...
LAGAT: He was courageous.
LAGAT: 他真有勇气。
He said, "I'm going to give 100 percent."
他说：“我会全力以赴。”
And he did.
他确实出尽全力了。
HERMENS: The three most important points from Monza were
HERMENS: 我们在蒙扎赛道得到的三点重要的经验是
that we didn't get enough carbohydrates inside Eliud.
一是我们没有给埃鲁德补充足够的碳水化合物
The drinks didn't work as we wanted.
饮料补给没有达到我们预想的效果
The weather was not ideal. The rain. And it was very humid.
二是天气不太理想，下雨了，而且天气很潮湿
And the other thing for Eliud was always the crowd.
最后一点影响到埃鲁德的是现场氛围
There was nobody there.
赛道旁完全没有观众围观
But that's also part of sports, you know
不过，这些问题本身也是运动的一部分
If we can predict everything, why are we here
如果我们可以预测到所有情况，那还要我们干什么？
You know, this is life.
人生就是充满各种意外的。
He almost succeeded, but he missed by 25 seconds.
他差点就成功了，仅仅差了25秒。
作为运动员，我们都会面临各种挑战
但如果你理解了失败对于人生的意义
那你就能从容地面对失败了
失败是人生的一部分
你输了，但你需要从中吸取教训
CHOGE: It was a learning curve for me.
配速员Choge：这对我来说也是个学习的过程。
He showed me a different character of himself.
他向我们展示了他的另一面
That the mind that we thought was, "He has a strong mind,"
那就是我们认为他所拥有的坚强意志
was stronger than we thought.
比我们想象中的还要更坚强
我们的目标是打破2小时大关
但是我失败了
不过，距离成功，就差25秒了。
LAGAT: The most successful people are the ones that are not afraid of fear.
LAGAT：最成功的人，是那些可以直面恐惧的人。
They try, and if they fail, they come back again.
他们不断地尝试、遭遇失败，然后再次尝试
NDUHIU: That belief that he has that no human is limited...
NDUHIU：他所信奉的“人类没有极限”。
It means, once you train your mind on something, you will achieve it.
意味着，一旦你在内心当中坚信一件事，你终将可以达成。
COE: The difference between the good and the great
COE：“成功”和“伟大”之间的差异在于：
is that your head may be telling you you possibly can't do it,
也许是你的理智告诉你“这事你干不成”，
but there is something else there
但还有另外一个声音
that overrules all those cautious thoughts.
会盖过其他不自信的想法，
And you think, "Fuck it, I can. And I'm gonna go for it."
你脑海都是“我X，干就是了！”
LAGAT: We're in a different era right now
LAGAT：我们当下处在一个独特的时代
where people believe these guys like Eliud are actually making sure
人们相信像埃鲁德这样的人正在创造历史
that the generation that will follow
让我们的后辈跟随
are going to think, "We are going to be running 2:00
并相信他们也可以在正式的马拉松赛中跑进2小时内
on an open marathon, or that is not going to be good enough."
而且会跑得更快
COMMENTATOR: Haile Gebrselassie writes yet another chapter
解说员：格布雷西拉西耶（长跑皇帝）在长距离赛跑的历史中
in the most astonishing distance-running career in history.
开启了一个时代。
HERMENS: In 2008, Haile Gebrselassie ran for the first time under 2:04 in Berlin.
2008年，格布雷西拉西耶在柏林马拉松首次跑进了2小时04分
（当时创世界纪录的精确时间：2:03:59）
Then more and more people are asking, "Two hours, when will it happen"
然后越来越多人在问，什么时候能够跑进2小时？
If you look at the curve of the marathon records,
然而如果你回顾过往的马拉松记录
it would take another 30, 40 years.
也许要再过30-40年吧
RATCLIFFE: To do the impossible... and I almost still believe
RATCLIFFE：作为一个跑者，我基本可以确定
that breaking a two-hour marathon is impossible, because I run!
马拉松跑进2小时以内是不可能的
And the idea of running every kilometer at two minutes 50
在我看来，
is impossible in my view.
要达到每公里2:50配速是不可能的
That requires this combination of an athlete that is truly superhuman,
这需要一个超人一般的运动员
but also incredibly meticulous organization
以及精确严密的组织规划
to get him to the point where he could break two hours.
两者结合才能才能打破2小时的大关。
It was that feeling of, "Holy shit, this is the real deal."
这感觉就是：“X，这回我们要来真的了！”
We've got this responsibility to this athlete
我们要担起重任，全力支持埃鲁德
who's only going to get this one chance.
让他实现突破
When you're going into something at the highest level,
当你在某项运动当中达到了最高的水准
you're really under a huge amount of pressure,
你会承受非常大的压力
you have to have done the preparation.
你必须做好充足的准备
You have to know in your mind that you've done all you possibly can.
你必须在方方面面都要做到最好
BRAILSFORD: In the first instance, you pull together a little team of people,
BRAILSFORD: 首先，你要组建起一个小队
your safe team, as it were...So, obviously, we got Tim in.
譬如保障团队....因此，我们把Tim拉进来了。
Tim's background was in rowing,
Tim有划船、游泳的运动管理经验
swimming, and he is now the most decorated coach in cycling.
然后他现在是最著名的自行车教练之一
What he does have is a knowledge of performance physiology
重要的是，他有运动生理学的知识体系
and an ability to apply that to a range of sports.
和把这些知识运用到具体运动项目中的能力
One A and one B.
另外，A组出一人，B组出1人
BRAILSFORD: I met Valentijn,
BRAILSFORD: 我找来了Valentijn....
who is a performance manager and looks after Eliud and his team,
找他来做运动表现管理，负责照看埃鲁德和他的团队，
and we hit it off straight away.
我们一拍即合了。
One of the greatest challenges in the first instance, was to find the course.
开始时最大的挑战之一，是找到一条合适的赛道。
On that side we had Hugh Brasher,
在这方面我们找到Hugh Brasher
who many will know is the director of London Marathon.
伦敦马拉松的赛事总监
So you had Valentijn, Hugh and myself as a sort of senior management team.
所以我，Valentijn和Hugh组成了高级管理小组
And then there were other people in our team.
而且团队里有很多成员，包括
Fran Millar, obviously who works very closely with me.
如Fran Millar，她和我的工作关联非常紧密
Peter Vint who was in charge of all the cars and the lasers and the timing.
Peter Vint，负责管理引导车、计时和激光引导，
Spencer had got all the pacers
Spencer，负责管理所有配速员
and Robby Ketchell who'd worked on the Nike project.
Robby Ketchell，上次Nike的破二计划也有他，
I mean, a brilliant guy. A scientist, meteorologist, aerodynamicist.
他身兼科学家、气象学家、空气动力学家。
I mean, phenomenally bright guy.
这家伙超级聪明
And that's one of the challenges
当你要组建一个由不同领域不同运动的专业人士组成的团队
when you take experts from different fields and different sports
这本身就是一项大挑战
and you try and pull them together, you've got to have the chemistry.
你需要具备一种吸引力，把大家都聚在一起，
We're going to have to move fast, we're going to have to have open minds,
我们需要高效率、开放的思想
and communicate really, really frequently and move at pace.
以及频繁、步调一致的沟通
Timothy and Emanuel, you just...you start also behind.
包括Timothy and Emanuel，你们要在后排起跑
Because we are all on the starting line.
所有人都是在起跑线出发的
- We will not start in this formation. - Oh, yes.
我们并不是按现在这个队形起跑的。哦，收到。
We are starting on the line and then, boom, go...
我们在起跑线出发，然后马上组成队形，开干...
BRAILSFORD: Normally, we race to win. We win medals, we win races.
BRAILSFORD: 一般来说，我们为了赢而比赛，努力拿下各种各样的赛事和奖牌。
We go to the Olympics, or the Tour de France, we win stuff in competitions.
例如奥运、环法...我们在比赛里赢下各种头衔。
This event is different. This is about breaking a human barrier.
但这次不一样，这次是要去打破人类的极限
So we had to really think about this in a slightly different way
因此我们需要稍微不一样的思路
and make sure the philosophy of the whole attempt was based
并确保我们这次尝试是基于“运动表现优先”的心态
on a performance -first mentality.
“运动表现优先”
What's going to get us to that record What's going to help the performance
我们要做什么才能突破极限？有什么能帮助我们发挥出最佳表现？
And if we have to work harder, invest more, find a different way,
更多的精力、时间、资源，尝试不同的方法
find a different solution for all the other aspects of the event
那这些工作都必须围绕我们的目标去开展
that will fit around it, then that's what we'd do.
这就是我们的团队现在需要做到的事情。
He had run a fantastic time in the London Marathon,
他曾经在伦敦马拉松跑出梦幻般的成绩
and we thought, actually, if he ran no worse,
我们在想
the same physical performance that he did in London,
如果他能够保持跟伦敦马拉松一样的身体表现
then could we look for the marginal gains
那我们能不能寻找其他的边际效益？
The optimizers, as we'd call them.
这就是我们所说的“优化空间”。
So, make sure the surface of the road is absolutely perfect.
因此我们尽可能确保赛道有着最理想的路面状况，
Perfect weather conditions.
理想的天气状况。
We wanted the corners to be more than 32 meters' radius.
我们要让赛道弯角的转弯半径大于32米
What's the thermoregulation What's the fueling strategy
如何调节体温？如何安排补给策略？
What's the pacing strategy The aerodynamics
怎么制定配速计划？怎么进行空气动力学优化？
All of those elements were critical in essentially
所有的这些因素，在本质上是至关重要的
what, for me, would be marginal gains.
这就是我们所说边际效益。
HERMENS: We improve shoes, we improve drinks, all these things.
我们改进鞋子，我们改善饮料，如此这般
But that's natural.
不过这些都是一般操作了
In ten years, we will be again finding out more things, and different things.
但是10年后，我们还是会找到更多不同的、可以改进的东西
It's just a point in history where we are at at the moment
此刻，我们虽然只是处于整个人类历史中的一个节点
and we are speeding up a little bit of history.
不过，我们现在，确实是在推动历史的发展
HAUPTALLEE大道 奥地利 维也纳
RATCLIFFE: I always wanted it to be somewhere iconic
RATCLIFFE: 我总想找一条具有标志性的赛道
because it's such a special event.
毕竟这是一场与众不同的盛事
I didn't really want to be in an airfield in Norfolk, you know
我实在不想找譬如Norfolk的某个机场
Or somewhere in northern Germany because those were a couple of ideas.
或者德国北部某个赛车场这种无聊的地方
You get a flat course and it's very manageable
对，这些地方是很平坦，方便管理
because there's no people around, there's no traffic.
没有路人的干扰，不需要做交通管制
You have to deal with all that.
没那么多麻烦事要去处理
If you're going to do this, it should really be in an iconic location.
但如果你真的要满足以上这些要求，那确实应该要找个标志性赛道了
KETCHELL: This course is actually something really special.
KETCHELL: 这条赛道真的是很特别
When we came and saw it for the first time, all of us looked at it
当我们第一次来到，看到这条赛道的时候，
and said immediately, "I think we found our place."
我们马上就决定“就是这地儿了”
You come here and even before you think about all of the physics around it,
只要你一来到这里，在你开始准备试跑
and the environment that you are trying to run in,
或者在你评估各种环境因素之前
you get a feeling of, "This is somewhere I can run fast."
你就已经能觉得“嗯，可以喺呢度做东喜”（狗头）
It was June 13.
那天是6月13日
Thirteen minutes past eight, I've got the call. It's Vienna.
8点13分，我接到了电话，他们选定了维也纳
It starts me crying a little bit, just for a moment.
那一刻我激动得直掉眼泪
To have Eliud here, and all those pacemakers
埃鲁德还有他的那些配速员要来这里破纪录
It was the best that ever could happen for Vienna.
那是维也纳的无尚光荣
So on this circuit, we have a 4.3 kilometer section here
这条环线上，我们现在正走着的这段
that we are walking on almost perfectly flat.
有4.3公里长，近乎全平的路段
It only has an elevation change of about 2.4 meters
这段路两端的高低差
from one end to the other.
总共只有2.4米
He's going to do 4.4 laps on it,
他要跑4.4圈
so that means that he is going to do this about 8.5 times.
也就是要在这段大直路上跑8趟半
And there are roundabouts that are located conveniently on either side.
然后，在大直路两端都有环形路给他掉头
Just having that circuit there was enough for us to decide
仅仅是路况就足以让我们
that this is an optimal location.
选定这里作为最合适的赛道了
When you approach anything like this, a big undertaking,
当你执行这么一类大工程
it's like being in a field where there's mist and you can't see anything.
这过程就好像身处于被浓雾笼罩的旷野
You don't know where the fence is or where the edges are.
你不知道哪里才是到头
But you know there's a gate somewhere. You know you can get out of the field.
但你知道总有一个出口可以走出去的，就是不知道在哪
But until the fog lifts, you're not going to be able to find the gate.
但是除非等到雾气散去，你才能找到出口
And it felt like that at the beginning of the project.
这个计划开始的时候，我就有这样的云山雾罩的感觉
And as the fog lifted,
然后等到雾散了
it was literally like all of the elements started to fall into place.
所有的安排都到位了
An order fell across the whole project.
一切都按顺序，工作有条不紊地进行
People really seemed to buy this concept
大家都开始相信
of, "We're doing something that no one has ever done."
“嗯，我们在做的这件事，前无古人”
Like, that's special. That's unique.
“独一无二”
There was a genuine magic to it, you know
这种想法把大家都深深吸引住了
世上没有事情可以做到百分百
但我可以保证，我现在很平静
我十分期待周六能做出点成绩来
BRAILSFORD: He is Zen-like in his approach and his preparation.
BRAILSFORD: 他在筹备的过程中，进入了有点禅定的状态
And watching him at close quarters develop
在他近距离地观察他的话，
from the end of the finishing line in the London Marathon,
会发现从伦敦马拉松冲线，
in those few months coming up,
到现在的这几个月里，
coming up to the level of when he was ready
是别的一些东西
to execute that performance, was something else.
促使他为此做好了准备。
How he approached that was very special.
他的做法很特别
Not only did he believe in himself, he had a brilliant way
不止是相信自己，他还能有办法
of making everybody around him believe in him, too.
让他身边的人都对他充满信心
The impact that has on everybody else around him in a project...
他能让计划团队里的每一个人都感受到他的自信，
Not only the other support runners and the pacemakers,
无论是他的支援队、配速员
but all of the staff, the coaching staff, the experts,
还是其他工作人员、教练团、专家们
everybody who was working night and day
所有人在他的影响下，都日以继夜
to try and bring all this project together, that's special.
团结一致把整个计划实现出来了，他真的是很厉害。
破2计划前夜，凌晨2点我就醒了，睡不回去
睡一阵 醒一阵
反反复复睡睡醒醒
就这样闹腾到4点40，我就完全醒过来了
6点到7点15那一阵，每个人都绷得很紧，准备开跑
我自己就很安静，也不跟人说话
到了7点15分，我们开始出去热身
慢jog了25分钟
MALE TV CREW: OK, good luck, Gabs. Here we go.
好，祝大家好运，Gabs，开波
FEMALE TV CREW: Cameras, keep offering what you can. Thank you.
镜头，尽量保持输出，唔该
Seven... six... five...
倒数7、6、5
three... two...
3、2
one.
COMMENTATOR: Well, the waiting is over. The moment has arrived.
好了，等咗咁耐终于开波啦！
We are just moments away. And there he is.
准备起跑啦，镜头见到，佢嚟啦！
You know, thousands, if not millions, of people
今日系星期六，出来跑步嘅人
will be going out for a Saturday run today.
无一万都有几千
Well, this could be the most famous Saturday run the world has ever seen.
不过，今日喱场周末跑将会系名垂青史
And it's all about this man, Eliud Kipchoge from Kenya.
因为，今日跑嘅人，系佢，肯尼亚人埃德鲁·基普乔格
ELDORET 肯尼亚 挑战日
MAN: [ON SPEAKER] The sub two hour marathon is considered
马拉松跑进2小时
the Everest of distance running.
堪比长跑界的珠穆朗玛峰
Something that people, for a long time, thought was nearly impossible,
很多人在很长一段历史里，在我们有生之年
we wouldn't see in our lifetimes.
都无法突破了
And in the last few years, it's suddenly hoved into view.
然而，过去这几年，我们突然间好像看到了希望
And we might see it today. It's very exciting.
今天，我们就要实现突破了，系唔系好激动呢！
[QUIET CHATTER]
吱吱喳喳 滋滋阵阵
[ "OBIERO" BY AYUB OGADA]
歌名
COMMENTATOR 1: We've already got crowds
镜头见到啊，赛道旁边已经有围观群众过来了
who are all expectant of history being made today in Vienna.
今日喺维也纳喱度，我哋全部都系历史见证人
COMMENTATOR 2: He's done everything there is to do in this sport.
佢系长跑运动已经创下了所有记录
This is the last barrier. The two-hour marathon.
宜家，剩低最后一个难关，2小时马拉松
This would be his legacy.
佢会开创一段传奇
COMMENTATOR 1: Every i has been dotted, every t crossed.
好了，万事俱备，箭在弦上
Is he going to do it
佢做唔做到呢？
The weather, the fact that it's foggy, a bit foggier than expected,
天气，老实讲系有d雾，比预期要湿d
throws another little doubt, maybe, into the minds.
令人感到多少有d唔舒服
This is not a foregone conclusion.
因为天气无预期中咁理想
我成个人好轻松
因为我的状态经过4-5个月的训练 已经达到顶峰了
所有训练目标都做到了
无伤、愉快
所以我精神上很放松、平静
做好准备，做嘢
COMMENTATOR: So we are into the final few minutes before countdown.
好啦，距离起步倒数仲有些少时间
- MAN: Fifteen seconds.
- WOMAN: Stand by, everyone.
—倒数15秒
—各位，醒定
Stand by three, stand by five.
3号机位准备，5号机位准备
- MAN: Here we go.
- WOMAN: Stand by ten.
—好，load机！
—10号机位准备
RUTO: From the president to the simple Kenyan in a village,
上至总统，下至肯尼亚的小村居民
we want to witness history being made.
我哋都想要见证历史的诞生
And we are confident that today, God willing,
我哋好有信心，耶稣保佑，
we will have a celebration
今日，我哋一定可以成功，开香槟！
and 1:59 is going to be a reality. Thank you very much.
1小时59分，一定会实现的！谢谢大家！
COMMENTATOR: We have lift-off. Apollo Kipchoge is up and away.
起跑！神舟火箭Kipchoge号起飞啦！
SANG: The race, when it started, it was beautiful.
作为教练，我从他的肢体动作可以看出
As a coach, you know, you look at the body language.
起跑状态很好，很完美
I saw the eyes of Eliud in the camera and he was very focused and relaxed.
我看着镜头里的Kipchoge，眼神很集中，整个人是放松的
Everybody was psyched up. The pacers were in high spirits
每个人都充满电，配速团队个个都精神饱满
and I said, "It's going to be a good day."
我跟旁人说，“今天是个出成绩的好日子！”
GRACE KIPCHOGE: When he started the race, I was nervous.
他起跑的那一刻，我很紧张
But when I saw how he was running,
但看到他的跑姿
he was really in good shape, and the pacers were also.
他的状况真的很好，其他配速员也很稳
LYNNE KIPCHOGE: I was nervous... exciting...
我很紧张、很激动
And...
还有
I had faith that he could do it.
我对他很有信心，他一定可以成功的
KERRISON: We had a starting-race plan. If everything went perfectly,
我们的赛事计划是，如果一切顺利的话
the plan was to go at the first kilometer at 2:48:00.
用2分48秒整跑完头一公里
And every other kilometer after that 2:50:45
然后剩下的路程每公里用时2分50秒45
which would give a finish time of 1:59:50.
这样算下来，冲线的时间就是1小时59分50秒
MALE COMMENTATOR: The speed at which they are traveling
他们现在的行进速度
is quite extraordinary.
好似搭火箭咁快
It's worth trying to put it into some sort of layman's terms.
简单d讲啦
He is going to be running, or trying to run, consistently
佢要全程保持速度不变，keep住
at 13 miles an hour.
时速13英里或者
Twenty-one kilometers an hour.
时速21公里一路跑到终点
FEMALE COMMENTATOR: It's mind blowing.
真系超乎想象啊
I challenge people to go to their local track
各位观众你地不妨试下，系你附近的400米跑道
and just run one lap, 400 meters of the track, in 68 seconds.
试一下用68秒，就跑1圈，
I bet you not many people can do that!
我相信没有几人能做得到！
This is crazy!
痴线噶！
MALE COMMENTATOR: We can break this down in so many ways.
我们来分析一下这个事情
One lap of the track, at your local track, 68 seconds.
你附近的田径场，68秒一圈，
And he has to do that 105 times. Each hundred meters in 17 seconds.
然后跑105圈，即喺用17秒跑完100米
And he will be doing that 422 times.
他要保持这个速度，跑422次
BRAILSFORD: We are very familiar in cycling with the concept of aerodynamics
我们在自行车运动上已经广泛应用空气动力学原理
and riding behind another one. A teammate taking the brunt of the wind
就是跟车。队友在前方承受风阻
and having to really tire themselves out
队友竭尽全力去破风
so the person behind can be fresher and then try and go for the win.
而后方的人的风阻就小了，能够留力夺取最终胜利
So Robby and the aerodynamics team
Robby和空气动力学团队
set about looking at the formations that were traditional in running.
就在传统的破风队形的基础上
And, also, throwing out some creative ideas.
增加了一些改进
They ran their CFD models, and their computer models,
他们采用电脑制作计算流体力学模型，
and we made models, and the miniature models went in the wind tunnel.
把这些模型做成缩小版模特，放在风洞里
Positioned them all, etcetera.
摆出各种队形，这样那样
Lo and behold, they came back and they said,
哇一声！结果出来了
"Actually, we found something pretty interesting."
“老老实实，我哋发现d好犀利嘅嘢”
KETCHELL: In a typical marathon, if he was to run by himself,
如果某个人自己一个人跑一场常规的马拉松
he would have about six Newtons of drag.
他要承受大约6牛顿的风阻
We've come up with a formation that has reduced that to about one Newton.
我们研究出一种破风队形，可以把风阻降低到大约1牛顿
It's a huge improvement in the drag that he'll have when he's running.
这大大减轻了Kipchoge在跑动中承受的负荷
So the pacers have a huge impact
因此在配速团队的全力帮助下
on being able to help Eliud break two hours.
Kipchoge就能突破2小时极限
Come on, guys!
加油啊兄弟们
HERMENS: I was there when he did the test in the winter,
冬天那次试跑，我也在现场
and it was fascinating to know.
原来我还以为，
We always thought pacemaking would be like the birds flying in the sky
配速员的队形会像鸟群飞行那种
in the open-V formation.
大V字型
But it turned out not to be a V.
但实际上不是V字型，
It turned out to be a Y.
而是像个Y字
KETCHELL: There are five runners in front of Eliud and two behind him.
在Eliud前面有5人，身后2人
The front-runners will be positioned over here on the sides
跑在最前面的配速员就在这个位置
and there will be two of them.
在Eliud的两边排好
But there will be a gap in between them which is not natural.
但是他们之间要刻意保持一点距离
That's part of the reason that training them how to run like this was difficult.
要保持距离这个是训练中的难点
Behind those two runners will be two more runners
头两个之后还有两个配速员
that are positioned further in, so we're starting to create a V.
然后他们之间的距离要窄一点，开始呈V字形了
Then, behind them will be the captain who runs in front of Eliud.
在他们后面就是配速队长，他跑在Eliud的正前方
BRAILSFORD: At some point, Fosbury did his flop for the first time.
当年Fosbury首次采用背越式参加跳高赛
And people went, "What What's he doing"
其他人都说“哈？佢搞乜春啊？”
And yet it worked.
结果，背越式现在人人都在用
So we said, "Why isn't this the Fosbury flop of running"
所以我们觉得，这Y字形破风阵，说不定就是马拉松里的背越式，能起作用的
We were maximizing what we call the outwash around each runner.
我们这队形，就是为了把跑者周身的空气绕流效益最大化
So the outwash means that when wind hits a runner on the torso,
当风吹在跑者的躯干上，空气就会绕过跑者
it changes the direction of the wind, and it's going to go out to the sides.
往两边流走
So, in effect, what was happening,
于是，当空气往队形最前面
the air was hitting the guy that was on the outside.
的配速员身上撞去的时候
Some of the air was coming outside, some was going inside.
会分流出两股气流，一股流向外侧，一股流向内侧
A guy on the inside of him, on his shoulder,
流向内侧的气流就会撞向第二排
was then getting the air coming from guy number one,
处于内侧的配速员的肩膀，而第二排的配速员本身
plus the air hitting him. So quite a lot more air, in fact.
也承受了吹向他自己正面的风，那个风压已经不小了
And, of course, this is happening on two sides of the funnel, as it were.
这只是位于漏斗的两侧
So the air, eventually, was funneled right into the middle,
而这些绕流最终会引导到位于队形中间的配速员面前
and the guy who was in the center in the middle, took a lot of air.
这位配速员承受的压力最大
He was getting quite a buffeting!
那可是堪比直面狂风般的压力
And what happened was, it created a big wake.
最终，这队形产生了一股大气流
It actually created a nice little hole where there was pretty much still air.
让Eliud的周围形成一小圈相对静止的空气（如同台风眼）
KETCHELL: In that wake is where Eliud needs to try to run
在那圈气流内，Eliud要尽量
as close to the captain in front of him.
紧随他前方的配速队长，尽量贴近
Typically, you wouldn't run there. Your visibility isn't the best.
一般情况下你不会紧贴前方的人来跑，会影响视线
You also don't want to trip.
也不想被前方绊倒
So you don't want to step on the runner in front of you.
也不想踩到前面的人
They'll kick back and vary a little bit.
前面的人也可能踢到后面，干扰到身后的人
COMMENTATOR: The absolute trust
解说员：毫不夸张地说，这把人之间
between all eight people at any one time cannot be overstated.
的绝对的信任，让他们分秒不差。
Bernard Lagat there, right at the heart of it, the initial captain.
起跑就带队的配速队长Bernard Lagat就在队形的中心
And he will be handing over shortly to the second team
他很快就会交接给第二队
and Eric Kiptanui will be the second captain.
第二队由Eric Kiptanui带领
COMMENTATOR 2: This event was always going to have a bit of ballet about it.
解说员2：这活动总多少有点像编排芭蕾舞
You needed everyone to know what they were doing, what their steps were.
你需要让所有人知道他们在干什么，他们的步伐如何。
We said, "OK, it's a big risk, we haven't got much time.
我们说：“好吧，这风险很大，我们没有太多时间”
We'll have to practice this thing. If we go with this,
我们将必须训练这些事情。如果我们真要这么做
then we want to make sure, as much as we can, that it's right."
那我们想要竭尽全力确保这是正确的。
LAGAT: It is kind of tricky,
LAGAT：这有点棘手
but then, as a captain, I need to keep my guys calm.
但是，作为队长，我要让我的队友们保持镇定
I want to make sure that they understand the formation, to stay in their lanes.
我要确保他们掌握队形的布局，为了让他们保持在自己的跑线上。
At the same time, note that they are the ones controlling the pace in the front.
同时，注意他们是在前面控制配速
SANG: The captain was the leader. He was in charge of all the pacers
桑：队长是指挥员。他负责确保所有配速员
to make sure they executed exactly what they were supposed to execute.
做到他应该做到的事情
我有一个很棒的团队
团队成员每个人都各司其职
我的工作就只是跟随配速团队前进
This is like the queen bee, protected by the drones and the others
这像是雄峰和其他工蜂在保护蜂后
and it's that beautiful thing, the exchange of the pacemakers!
配速团队的交替安排确实是干得漂亮
COMMENTATOR: And we're keeping an eye out here
解说员：现在大家注意了
for the first change-over.
准备进行第一次配速队伍的替换
As I think Shalane was likening... Here we go!
我想Shalane是在把它比作…开始了！
Shalane, talk us through this.
Shalane，给我们说明一下吧
SHALANE: Yeah, I was likening it to, in the US, a NASCAR pit stop,
Shalane：好呀，我将其比作纳斯卡汽车大赛的维修站
where we change our tires, fine tune the machine...
在那里我们更换车胎、微调机器…
Same thing goes here for Eliud.
他们把类似的操作，用在了Eliud身上
He's switching out and getting fresh runners
上一个团队现在散开，空出位置让新的配速员能够
that are hopefully smoothly transitioning into formation
顺畅地替换进队形里
so that Eliud can just draft, and conserve as much energy as possible.
这样能让Eliud留在空气尾流中，尽量保存更多的体力
BRAILSFORD: Those changes were not easy.
BRAILSFORD：每次队形替换都很不容易
One slip, one wrong turn with a trip-up, and it could all be over.
一次滑倒，一次拐错弯绊倒，都可能导致失败
We wanted to maintain the pace
我们想在配速队撤出和接替的同时，
as well as the team exiting and the team coming in.
依然保持着前进的速度
So we want the team that is going out
所以我们需要前一队
to really move out smoothly and maintain the pace.
在不减速的同时流畅平稳地外撤
Then we also want the team going in to come in smoothly,
然后下一队平稳地接替队形的同时
not distracting Eliud.
不能干扰到Eliud的节奏
RATCLIFFE: We probably have 40 of the top athletes on the planet
RATCLIFFE：我们召集到40位地球上最顶尖的运动员
and they're all working for a common cause
来帮助Eliud
and one man, which is Eliud.
向着同一个目标发起冲击
COMMENTATOR: The man at the heart of it,
解说员：在队伍中间的这个人
he's already the world record-holder,
是现任世界纪录保持者
and he is surrounded by his band of brothers.
而围绕在他身边的“兄弟连”里面，
We've got 15 Kenyans, seven Americans, six Ugandans.
15个肯尼亚人，7个美国人, 6个乌干达人。
We've got Australians, Norwegians, Ethiopians and one Japanese pacemaker.
澳大利亚的、挪威的、埃塞俄比亚的，还有一位来自日本的配速员
It really is a truly international field.
这的确是一场国际盛事
SHALENE: They all idolize and look up to Eliud.
SHALENE：他们都视Eliud为偶像
I think they look at this as a chance to be a part of history today.
他们把今天能参与这个事情视为他们也有机会成为（创造）历史的一部分。
It's a beautiful opportunity to help someone
一次绝佳的时机，去帮助一个，能把这项运动
that we know can transcend our sport.
升华到一个更高境界的人
WANDERS: You know, running is the most natural sport in the world.
WANDERS: 我们天生就会跑步
You grow up, you walk, you run.
你长大了，自然而然就会走路，然后就会跑步
I think that's why this sport is so beautiful.
我认为这是这项运动的美妙之处
You can run without shoes. You don't need anything to run.
你不需要穿鞋，什么都不需要，就能跑。
想要在生活中获得自由（好像就只有跑步了）
跑步就是人类的天性，落后国家的人，
或者这个世界的某个角落的某个人，站起来，然后迈开步，跑起来
或者站起来，开展工作，然后创造奇迹
SHALENE: From an African perspective,
SHALENE：从一名非洲人的角度看，
right now, there are young Africans watching,
此时此刻，很多年轻非洲人在关注着这件事
and just looking to see what human potential looks like,
他们正在期待见证人类的潜能巅峰
waiting to be the next Kipchoge.
期待着自己也可以成为下一个Kipchoge
This is so inspiring, not only to runners all over the world,
这极其振奋人心，不仅对世上所有的跑者
but to everybody, that no human is limited.
更是让每个人都感受到，人类没有极限。
You can go for your goals
你也可以追求自己的目标
if you have that energy and that strong mind
如果你拥有那能量与强韧的意志
that you do whatever you want to do.
便能随心所欲。
So it's not about running.
所以这不只是创造跑步的历史
It is about inspiring the world
更是激励着世界上的每一个人
everybody else in the world that everything is possible.
告诉他们，一切皆有可能
And nothing is limited for you.
你，没有极限
COMMENTATOR: We are approaching the first of the roundabouts here.
解说员：他们来到第一个回旋处
This is the Lusthaus. This is the smaller of the two roundabouts.
这里是Lusthaus，这是两个环岛之一中的较小者。
In the middle of that is a former hunting lodge.
在这中间的，以往是一间狩猎小屋。
KETCHELL: The turn radius around the Lusthaus on average
KETCHELL：Lusthaus环岛的平均转弯半径
is about 27.4 meters.
大约是27.4米。
Originally, when we came here, the surface was pretty old.
当我们第一次来到这，看到路面有点残破
We knew that we were going to resurface.
所以肯定要重新铺路
When you're running at 5.861 meters per second
当你以5.861米每秒的配速
at a 27.4-meter radius
跑过一个半径27.4米的弯而不掉速
you would, optimally, be looking for about a ten-degree banking.
理想的状态下，路面应该向弯心倾斜10度
In a real-world condition, we can't create a ten-degree banking,
但在现实中，我们无法弄出一条倾斜10度的路面
but we can do something to improve the current situation
现在的情况是，Eliud跑在这个弯位时，身体会呈-2%的倾角。
of there being a negative two percent of a camber going away from Eliud.
不过我们可以在现有的路面基础上做出改进
LAGAT: If you think of a track athlete who runs indoors
LAGAT: 就像是有个田径运动员，在室内跑步
you run on a 200 -meter banked track.
跑道是200米的弯道
Now, if you're going fast, if it was flat at 200 meters,
假如这200米跑道是水平的，然后你用全力地跑的话
you're going to drift towards the outside.
渐渐地你会往弯道外侧飘出去
You're allowed to step off the lines,
你可以在跑线外落脚
but you'd want a little bit of a cushion.
但是你想要有一点缓冲效果（踩在线上）
- Yeah, I'm sure you saw me going... - Yeah, yeah, I was, like...
对呀，我相信你看到我会…对对对，我是，就像是…
WANDERS: It's a bit dangerous when you arrive at such a turn,
WANDERS：当你以高速度，跑进这样一个弯道
when you run at a fast pace.
多少有点危险
You might slip a little bit outside or even twist your ankle.
你整个人会往外飘，甚至可能扭到脚踝
They have actually raised it,
所以他们把那段路面垫高了一点
so that as you're running there,
这样当你跑到那里时
you feel like you're running an indoor track.
你会感觉像是跑在室内跑道一样
You're supported and you're staying balanced.
有一种支撑感、整个人都很稳
KETCHELL: It changes it from negative two percent to a positive one percent
KETCHELL：我们把它从-2%改成了+1%的倾角
so we get a three -percent difference.
这样就获得了一个与原来相比3%的斜度差
We estimate that it can save him up to three seconds per lap.
我们估计每圈能为Eliud节省3秒钟
So that's 12 seconds over the entire distance.
那全程来讲就是缩短12秒了
He won't save that time,
你也可以说这并不会节省时间
because he actually won't run quicker because of that
因为垫高跑道不会让他跑得更快
but he will conserve more energy.
但是这会帮助他保存体力
That's going to allow him to run at the sub two-hour pace for longer.
以求将破二的配速维持得更久
COMMENTATOR: OK, you can see the recent splits there.
解说员：好，我们看到了最新的分段时间
The 2:50 mark in green
当前分段是 2分50秒，路边电子牌显示绿色
means that he is on schedule for a sub two-hour marathon pace.
意味着Eliud的破二计划的推进很顺利
2:52 and 2:51 in the red, means he's just outside.
如果是红色的标志，显示2分52、2分51这样，说明他稍稍低于计划配速了
He's been twice on target, and twice just outside.
到现在他拿到了两个绿标，两个红标
It just shows us, Ed, even in these early stages,
你就可以感受到挑战有多大了
just how challenging it is.
而且现在才开始没多久！
KERRISON: So, in what we call the POC, on the day of the race,
挑战当天，在POC（一个缩略语）
the Performance Operations Center,
也就是传说中的中央指挥所
we had representatives from the aerodynamics team, the pacemakers team,
荟聚了各团队负责人 有空气动力学团队、配速员团队
the car and the laser, the timing system, the meteorology team,
也有引导车组，镭射激光组、计时组、气象组
and myself in communication with Valentijn on the road.
我个人则负责联络骑车机动的Valentijn
Any information that needed to come from any of those specialist teams
POC的专家们需要告诉Valentijn些什么
to Valentijn was done through me.
都由我来一一转达
COMMENTATOR: Communication taking place
解说员：后方中心传消息
with Valentijn on the bicycle. He's giving instructions out.
给Valentijn了，他现在把指令转达出去
BRAILSFORD: I mean, it looks like one smooth event, doesn't it？
Brailsford：所有东西看起来都挺顺利对吧？
[LAUGHS] But it's a million miles from that, you know.
哈哈哈哈哈哈哈哈顺利个鬼
KERRISON: We had some interesting situations in the race
Kerrison：赛事中状况频发，
where even the second kilometer, we thought was out.
我们以为第二个1公里落后于计划时间了
There were some kilometers that were 2:48 and some that were 2:52.
因为有几段跑出了248，又有几段是252
2:48! That's like... [SIGHS] They've gone out too fast.
248配速--[丢] 比计划快了！
TROUW ON RADIO: That's the correction from the 2km board. Over.
电台回传：2公里提示板的显示数字改过来了
This is a major issue.
这是大事故啊
In our little Mission Control pod,
在我们那个小小的控制舱里面已经炸开了锅
it might have been looking like a start to an event to everyone else.
外人可能觉得问题不大，才开始嘛
"Oh, they're getting going, getting warmed up."
“呐，不跑得挺好的吗，都还在热身呢，不急～”
We were, like, "Whoa, OK, there's something...
我们淡定不下来，“糟了，摊上事了。”
What's going on
哪儿出问题了呢？
Tim Kerrison is sitting there with his headphones on.
Tim Kerrison，本来戴着耳机的
And he kind of nonchalantly took one off
突然摘下半边耳机
and put it on the side and said,
撂在耳朵一旁，冷冷地说道
"All this timing you're seeing on the telly, and that everyone can see,
“显示屏上的这些时间、这些数字，你看得到，其他人也看到”
"it's wrong."
“这些数字都错了。”
I was like, "What" He said, "Yeah, it's wrong.
“真的假的？”他说“珍珠都没这么真，是计时搞错了，
They're on pace."I said, "Are you sure"
他们的配速没问题。”我说，“你真的确定？”
He said, "Absolutely. I'm right.
“数据绝对是错的，信我”
We're going to switch to our back-up time and do it ourselves."
“赶紧切换到后备计时，我们手动计时”
I was, like... [CLEARS THROAT]
然后...[清喉咙] 我说
"OK, everybody. Forget the timing. We're switching to back-up timing."
“各位，现在别管自动计时了，我们切换到备用计时系统”
Two-51.
2分51秒
COMMENTATOR: The target time holding up pretty well.
解说员：现在他们仍然按着计划时间去跑，
We've been hovering between eight and ten seconds
相对破二的模拟进度，队伍目前有着
inside sub two-hour pace.
8到10秒的优势
So, so far so good.
所以，一切都还顺利
And, Ed, the next real milestone will be the ten-kilometer mark.
是的，Ed，下一个关键点就在10公里处
And sub two-hour pace would put him at, what, 28:26.
按照2小时内的配速，他跑到10公里的时间就是 28分26秒
ED: Yeah, which is a prettytidy10K!
ED：是的，那是一个相当利落的10公里!
COMMENTATOR: Just out of picture is Valentijn Trouw the athletes'manager
解说员：刚刚离开画面的Valentijn Trouw，运动员的经理
handing now more drinks and more gels to Eliud if he wants them.
如果Eliud要更多的饮料或能量胶的话，Valentijn负责给他递上
He does take something on board there.
而Eliud也确实在行进中补给了一些
KERRISON: How much he consumes is actually closely monitored
KERRISON：Eliud的营养师一直会
by his nutritionist who will be measuring
严密监控着他的补给量
every time that he takes something from his water bottle and tosses it.
每次他补给完，然后抛开水壶，
They will pick it up and hand it off to him
会有人把水壶捡起来，交给营养师进行称重
so he can weigh it and know how much he consumed.
然后就可以算出他吃进了多少补给
BRAILSFORD: We had people just there to grab that bottle
BRAILSFORD：我们安排了人手，
before it got in the crowd.
在水壶落入人群之前去把它捡起来
Get the bottle, get the bottle! Right, get it in.
拿好瓶子，拿好瓶子! 对了，把它拿进来。
What's the measurement How much did he drink
测量的结果是什么？他喝了多少？
You feed it back in. He took X amount of mls on that one.
把结果报告给中心，这瓶他喝了X毫升。
OK, we need to change the next one.
行，下一瓶补给的量要变一下
So they were modifying the fueling strategy in-race, live.
所以他们在赛中会实时调整补给的策略。
TROUW: To keep that same rhythm for two hours...
TROUW: 为了在两小时都保持同样的节奏...
That's a lot of things happening in your body, your muscles.
在你的身体里，你的肌肉里，有很多情况在发生
Some muscles, especially the hamstrings, will get very tight.
有些肌肉，特别是腘绳肌，会变得很紧。
Because you're running in the same rhythm.
因为你保持着相同的节奏去跑
Lactic acid is building up in the muscles.
肌肉里的乳酸会一直在堆积。
After one hour and a half, it will be very difficult for him.
而一个半小时后，对他来说，将会变得非常辛苦
Everyone was stressed not to do a mistake, not to make him fall.
每个人都很紧张，不能犯错，不能让他掉速
That was the worst that could happen.
掉速可是最糟糕的情况了
And when it was my turn, of course, I was stressed,
而当轮到我的时候。当然，我很紧张。
but I was so happy to be here to help Eliud.
但我很高兴能在这里来帮助Eliud。
I think I am getting the mindset of the Kenyans.
我想我现在已经能像一个肯尼亚人去思考了
Believing that everything is possible by just training every day
相信一切皆有可能，只要每天坚持训练
for months and months, years and years.
月复一月，年复一年。
When you go to race, you have this self-belief that you can win.
当你去参加比赛时，你有这种自我信念，你可以获胜。
I was more keen on the body language
我更热衷于肢体语言
as the race progressed because they never fell back.
虽然比赛正在进行着，他们也没有掉队
But, as far as making the right times were concerned,
但是，就做出正确的时间而言。
they were being guided by the laser.
前面有激光引导着他们。
COMMENTATOR: Some people have criticized, or maybe had a view about,
解说员：有些人已经批评了，或可能质疑
the role of the lead car, there.
那个引导车的（额外）作用
We can see perhaps that that's adding extra protection,
我们可以看到，也许那车帮忙挡了一点风。
but, essentially, as far as the experts have explained to us,
但是，专家说那车其实就是
the only reason that car is there is to project the laser pacer.
仅仅用来投射引导激光而已
COMMENTATOR 2: If you talked to Robby Ketchell who designed the aerodynamics
解说员2：据空气动力学设计师Robby Ketchell所说，
he said, "If it were up to me, I wouldn't have a car."
"如果由我来决定，我就不会安排那个车了。"
It doesn't seem like that would be right
不安排引导车的似乎也不好，
but all the computational flow dynamics that they have been doing
但根据专家们的流体力学计算
have told them that the best results would be without a car.
结果表明，不安排引导车才是最好。
The car, obviously, had the laser which set the pace-line
引导车用激光束划分来跑线
so they knew exactly at what pace to run.
所以他们可以按照激光指示来跑。
And it also had the lines to help them stay in the corridor, if you like.
也可以说是因为有了激光指示，可以帮他们跑在正确的位置上。
KETCHELL: The reason that it's 15 meters in front of Eliud
KETCHELL：引导车之所以要保持在Eliud前面15米，
is in order to throw the laser at a significant distance.
是为了把激光投到一个适当的距离。
Plus, in order to maintain the pace precisely.
另外，为了精确地保持速度。
It doesn't help the runners behind Eliud
这对Eliud 后面的跑者没有帮助。
and it doesn't help Eliud's position,
这对Eliud 所处的位置没有帮助。
but it helps those five guys
directly in front of him.
但这有助于Eliud面前的五个配速员保持速度。
COMMENTATOR: Let's just home in here on Eliud Kipchoge.
解说员：让我们把画面切回Eliud Kipchoge
This is a great shot for us to see the cadence,
这个镜头非常棒，我们看到了一种优美的韵律，
and the way the rhythm, the natural rhythm...
如此自然的行进
From memory, correct me, both of you, if I'm wrong,
我记得，如果我错了，你们两个请纠正我。
but I don't think we've had a kilometer outside 2:52.
他们每公里的完成时间都没有多过2分52秒。
- I think that's the slowest we've had. -SHALENE: Correct.
2分52秒已经是最慢的了。 -SHALENE：就是。
That's incredible.
真是难以置信。
If you really think about it, that is incredible pacing!
如果你真的仔细想想，这是令人难以置信的配速！
HERMENS: Eliud has trained himself incredibly well
HERMENS: Eliud训练得非常好，
to keep the same rhythm for two hours.
可以在两个小时内保持相同的节奏。
And the rhythm of all those different athletes is like a drum
这群运动员的节奏
hammering on the streets.
就像敲在赛道上的鼓一般
It reminds me of that same feeling
这让我想起
of them running in the long runs in Kenya.
他们在肯尼亚长跑时的同样感觉。
A kind of silence where you only hear the steps going on.
你只能听到脚步声的一种“静”。
For me, ja, it sounds to me like music.
对我来说，那听起来就如音乐一般动听。
[RUNNING FOOTSTEPS]
［奔跑的脚步声］
REPORTER: There are people who are a little bit cynical about this
记者：有些人会有点愤世嫉俗
and saying "Well, it's not an official world record,
说“嗯，这不是官方（承认）的世界纪录，
and there's so much technology, so much science, why should we care"
还有这么多的技术，这么多的科学，我们为什么要在意？
COMMENTATOR: There is something artificial about this
解说员：是，虽然这次破二是刻意为之，
but that's because they want to see one guy do what no one else has done before.
但那是因为他们想看到有人能达成这件前无古人的创举。
It would be incredibly hard to achieve this in an open race.
在正式的赛事中要做到这一点是非常困难的。
And so, I think there is room in the sport
所以，我认为无论是以这种形式还是公开赛
for both events like this, and also, like, open races.
都有进行这一挑战的空间。
London Marathon is fantastic, and this is fantastic.
伦敦马拉松非常棒，这次也非常棒。
REPORTER: Obviously, we know technology goes into sportswear
记者：显然，我们知道运动装备领域加入了高科技，
and has done for a very long time,
并且已经发展了一段很长的时间。
but we shouldn't underestimate what's going on on his feet,
但我们不能低估他脚下的鞋子，
and how important they are, those trainers.
以及这些鞋子的重要性。
COMMENTATOR: I don't think we should kid ourselves.
解说员：我认为我们不应该自欺欺人。
I don't think it would've been possible to try to go under two hours
五年或者十年前，我认为不可能在两个小时内
five or ten years ago.
完成马拉松的
The technology has developed so fast and he's in the latest innovation.
技术发展如此之快，他如今就穿着跑鞋技术的巅峰之作，
He's in shoes that no one else has ever run before.
他脚下的这双跑鞋，没有别人穿过。
It's a step change from where we were even two years ago.
这与我们两年前的情况相比有了很大的变化。
So, we're talking about, maybe, a few seconds
所以，我们正在讨论的是，哪怕只有几秒钟
which in this context is an enormous amount of help.
在这种情况下，也会有巨大的帮助。
REPORTER: It could be vital.
记者：这可是至关重要的。
REPORTER 2: World athletics are reportedly getting ready to
ban
记者2：世界田联正准备禁止耐克的Vaporfly跑鞋，
Nike's Vaporfly shoes for giving runners an unfair advantage.
因为它给穿着者提供了不公平的优势。
REPORTER 3: The introduction of the Vaporfly to the running community
记者3：将Vaportfly引入跑步社群
really has changed what we think of as possible.
确实改变了我们所能理解的跑步。
In very simplistic terms, it's almost like a mini pogo stick.
用非常简单的术语来说，它几乎就是一个迷你弹簧棒。
You put the shoe on and you're immediately aware that it's different.
你一穿上它，你会立即意识到它的不同。
Nike Sports research labs are working with Kipchoge
Nike运动研究实验室与Kipchoge展开合作，
on enhancing his shoes to break that two-hour mark.
改进他的鞋子，帮助他打破两小时的记录
REPORTER 4: But I guess the big question comes down to,
记者4:但我认为最大的问题就是，
if you're not wearing the Nike Vaporfly, can you compete
如果你不穿Nike Vaporfly，你还能突破吗？
REPORTER 5: These shoes certainly are game-changing and transformative.
记者5：这些鞋子改变了游戏规则，具有革命性的意义
The athletes typically are sponsored, always sponsored,
运动员的赞助商，
by only the shoe industry.
往往只有鞋企
So that industry controls the sport.
所以鞋企掌控着这项运动
COE: Some of the biggest sponsors of our sport are the shoe companies.
COE: 这项运动最大的几个赞助商都是鞋类公司
We don't really want to be telling them what they can and can't do.
我们真的不想告诉他们什么可以做，什么不能做。
But there are obviously things that we would be concerned about
但有些东西，明显是需要我们留意的，
if that technology started to become the predominant story.
那就是技术（取代运动员本身）开始成为运动发展的主导力量
REPORTER 6: I think the research right now shows actual Innovation
记者6：我认为目前的研究显示了科技的创新着实在
that blurs the line of enhancement.
模糊着运动进步的边界。
REPORTER 7: It enhances performance
记者7： 它提高了成绩
because it's such a technological sneaker.
因为这双运动鞋的科技含量相当高
REPORTER 8: The properties of the carbon fiber plate and...
记者8：碳纤板的性能和…
COE: No society, no market economy, has ever prospered
COE：没有哪个社会，也没有哪个市场经济
by trying to stifle innovation.
能够通过扼杀创新而获得繁荣。
I think, whether we like it or not,
我想，不管我们是否喜欢
technology comes into a lot of sports these days.
如今，技术手段已经进入了很多运动
I mean, look at cycling. The advances we've made in the bicycle.
我的意思是，看看自行车运动，我们在运动自行车上所做的那些技术改进。
Does that take anything away from Egan Bernal
Egan Bernal或Geraint Thomas是因为这些技术改进
or Geraint Thomas when they win the Tour de France
才赢得环法自行车赛的吗
They still need to ride it.
他们依然是要用力骑车才能赢的啊。
PITSILADIS: The world of sport needs to consider
PITSILADIS: 体育界需要考虑到
that the effects of technological doping
“技术型兴奋剂”的影响
are vastly superior than traditional doping.
远远优于传统兴奋剂。
So, therefore, you and I, the public,
所以，因此，你和我，还有公众
can no longer gauge what you're watching.
无法再衡量你们眼睛所看到的
鞋子是很好，不过
无论对我或其他人，是跑的人起到了决定作用
鞋子能够帮到我的方面主要是恢复
鞋子很轻
而且从沥青路面上吸收了很多冲击
但如果你不够强健，你跑不快
For anybody who says this isn't right, put the shoes on yourself.
对于任何不认同的人，请自己穿上鞋子试试。
Wear the same kit, get yourself down to Vienna,
穿上同样的装备，去维也纳
get a couple of people to run in front of you, and see how fast you go.
找几个人跑在你面前，看看你能跑得多快。
COMMENTATOR: Well, this is the sixth of nine teams.
解说员：嗯，这是9个配速团队中的第6个，
There are nine rotations, if you like.
一共有9次轮换，
And, there we are, Eric Kiptanui, who is having a busy old morning.
哦，来了，这是Eric Kiptanui，这个早晨他十分忙啊。
He's back on as the team captain.
他再次担任配速队长。
COMMENTATOR 2: I tell you, that guy is in shape!
解说员2：你看，这兄弟的身材可真不错！
NJOROGE: Technology has a place, and it helps.
NJOROGE: 技术有一席之地，它有帮助。
But, at the end, it is the human being.
但归根到底，（突破极限的）是人。
And I think that's what I find really amazing with Eliud.
我认为这就是我发现Eliud真正令人惊奇的地方。
At the end of the day, it is him. And he knows what really drives him
归根到底，是他。他知道驱使他去前进的
and it isn't the technology that will drive him.
并不是科技。
Sub two hours has everything to do with the changing of times,
破二与时代的变迁
changing of history, changing of sports in general.
历史的变迁、体育运动的变迁息息相关。
But what remains, there is a guy a fantastic athlete, Eliud Kipchoge,
但不变的是，有这么一位出色的运动员，Kipchoge
who is running 42 kilometers.
他跑了42公里。
Yes, there is some science involved
是的，这里面有科学的成分
but it's still a person that has to do this.
但这仍然是需要由某个人去完成的事情
生活在这个世界上，你不可能没有负能量
这些负能量也许是件好事
它让我们不断逼迫自己
SANG: I think Eliud did not land from another planet.
SANG: Eliud不是外星人。
We know what he has done, we know his potential.
我们知道他为了这一切做了什么，我们知道他的潜力。
He ran a world record in Berlin.
他在柏林创造了世界纪录。
And I think the opinions of people should be reflected in reality
我觉得这种（打破局限）看法会折射在现实中
of exactly the journey he has come through.
通过他经历的这场奇妙旅程
COMMENTATOR: I think there was a slight trip.
解说员：（Eliud）好像被小绊了一下
- Was there a trip - SHALENE: Yes.
是不是被绊了？SHALENE: 是
I just saw Eliud have a little trip-up in that transition.
我刚看到Eliud在（配速团队）转换中有被小绊了一下
COMMENTATOR: 12K to go, then.
解说员：接下来还剩下12K
This is where the critical stage of the race starts.
这场比赛的关键时刻正式开始了
We can make some comparisons with how he was going in Monza.
我们可以拿他在蒙扎赛道破二的状态做一下对比
Actually, up to halfway, he was inside sub two-hour pace.
那次在蒙扎赛道，在前半程阶段，他还是在破二的配速中
And at halfway exactly, he was three seconds inside
到达半程点，他还快了三秒钟
and then at 25K, he was still two seconds inside.
之后在25K，他仍然快了两秒
Even at 30K, he was only two seconds outside sub two-hour pace.
甚至在30K，他离破二的速度也只慢了两秒
And he admitted afterwards that it was in the final 10K
后来他也承认了，在最后的10K中
when he really started to feel it.
他开始感觉到了（掉速）
SHALENE: Literally no human has tried to attempt this.
SHALENE：真的从未有人去尝试这个
There's a lot of unknowns Physiologically
生理上存在很多未知因素
as to what Eliud can handle.
这些都是要Eliud去克服的
COMMENTATOR 2: He's putting himself through something
解说员2：他其实现在处于一种非比寻常的
really, really extraordinary here, and he will be emotional.
精神状态，此时此刻他将变得思绪纷乱
Thoughts bubble up. Thoughts you think you suppressed.
想法冒起又抑制，思绪翻腾
Bad demons sit on one shoulder and good angels sit on the other.
天人交战
KIPCHOGE: [ECHOES] The way you think about pain,
KIPCHOGE:【回声】你对待痛苦的方式
is the way your life will be.
造就了你的人生
In this world, you need to undergo pain in order to be successful.
在这世上，你想要成功须先经历苦痛
If you understand how marathon is,
如果你理解了马拉松是怎样
at the apex of the pain, that's where success is.
处在痛苦的顶点的，那就是成功的所在
SHALENE: In training, he has visualized these tough moments
SHALENE：在训练中，他有想像过这些艰难的时刻
and he's pushed through in training and said, "This is the crucial moment.
在训练中，他就已经把自己逼到了这种状态，他说：“这就是决定性的一刻，”
This is when you have to execute and push through the pain."
“这就是你必须经历和克服痛苦的一刻。”
So, he has practiced this over and over.
所以，他已经练习了一次又一次
COMMENTATOR: We've just detected the slightest smile-stroke-Grimace
解说员：我们刚刚看到了轻微的乔式笑容
on the face of Eliud Kipchoge.
出现在了他的脸上
When the smile appears, Shalane,
当这个笑容出现，Shalane,
that normally suggests that he's hurting.
通常代表了他正在经历痛苦
SHALENE: Yeah, that's the classic Eliud, when he is leaning into that hurt.
SHALENE:是的，这就是Eliud的经典表情，他正在经受着痛楚
It means he's working hard.
说明他正在努力坚持着
COMMENTATOR 2: He has to be thinking right now,
解说员2：他现在肯定正在想
and I'm sure this is a version of what he's thinking,
我肯定他一定有想过这个念头：
"If not now, when"
“此时此刻”
压力是非常大
但应对压力的方式更为重要
不求与人相比，只求超越自己
做自己，做东喜（狗头）
每个人都应该相信自己的能力
BRAILSFORD: He looked like he came through that moment.
BRAILSFORD：看起来他挺过去了
In the mission control, it was, like... [EXHALES]
我们在控制中心里，大家都【呼】（长吁一口气）
This is on. This is on now. This is coming!
来了，就是现在，终于要来了！
And it was exciting, like, "Oh!"
非常令人兴奋，像，“哇！”
It's just those moments, what you live for in sport!
这就是你的运动生命中所期待的那些时刻之一
COMMENTATOR: One and a half hours about to click round on the clock.
解说员：一个半小时过去了
We have just under 30 minutes to try and get Eliud Kipchoge
我们只有不到30分钟去见证Eliud Kipchoge
into the history books, here in Vienna.
在维也纳这里创造历史
And I can't stress enough,
我无法足够形容
the crowd out on the course is absolutely phenomenal.
赛道外人群的洋溢着热烈非凡的激情
听到观众的欢呼，以及那些在道路两旁奔跑、骑着车的人们，让人感觉非常振奋
SANG: He gives energy and he gets energy back.
SANG: 他发出了光和热的同时又得到了人们的回赠
And that is a wonderful place to be in.
这是一个美妙的地方
WOMAN: We Kenyans are very good as a cheer squad.
WOMAN：作为啦啦队，我们肯尼亚人非常在行。
It's all about the support at the back
我们就是支持着他的强力后盾，
that comes out shining to the whole world.
帮他在世人面前闪耀。
他的计划是非常困难的
他需要每个人站在那里
吹口哨、欢呼、鼓掌
BRAILSFORD: He has trained himself incredibly well for what is going on
他已经练到了可以有选择地
and what he takes in, and what he shuts down from the outside world.
接收需要了解的信息，屏蔽其他外界干扰
我尝试着仅去集中注意力
你懂的。当你听到有人在喊”你可以的！你可以的！“的时候
这不仅是对士气的鼓舞
同时也是一种压力
因为你无路可退了
COMMENTATOR: Here we go, this is team number eight.
解说员：第8组配速团队来了
Wow. I think we just need to take a pause, don't we, and just breathe
哇噢，我觉得我们需要暂停一下，换口气（紧张得忘记呼吸了）
COMMENTATOR 2: I feel very nervous right now.
解说员2：我现在非常紧张
Because anyone who has ever run a marathon
因为每一个跑过马拉松的人
will know that the last few miles,
都知道那最后几英里
anything can happen, and the wheels can come off.
什么事都有可能发生，很容易掉链子
He looks really good. You're just hoping that he's got this.
他看起来状态真的很好。就是你希望看到的那样。
COMMENTATOR: Here are the final team of pacemakers, team number nine.
解说员：第9组也是最后一组配速员来了。
They will take them home from 38 kilometers right through to the finish.
他们将要从38K处带领Eliud直到终点
And the captain, of course, he was the captain in the first team.
这组的队长，当然还是他，就是第1队的队长
It's Bernard Lagat.
Bernard Lagat
There he is, itching to go, Bernard Lagat.
Bernard Lagat过来了，他蓄势待发
And how fitting that the 44-year-old, the oldest pacemaker in the team,
这位44岁，队伍里年纪最大的配速员，状态绝佳
the most experienced and a dear, dear friend of Eliud,
他既是Eliud的密友，同时也是最有经验的配速员
should be the captain on the final leg.
担任最后一段的配速队长是当仁不让的。
We're on the verge of history here, folks.
诸位，我们正处在历史的转折点
KERRISON: We don't know what the limits of human performance are.
KERRISON: 我们不知道人类的是否有极限
There are people who think they do know
有的人说有
and remarkable humans, and teams of humans,
但是那些超凡杰出的人
keep proving them wrong.
不断地证明，他们错了。
BRAILSFORD: Our own individual performances
BRAILSFORD: 我们每个个体的能力
are nearly always linked to a collective performance somewhere.
几乎总是与集体的能力连在一起
And I think for all of us, in all walks of life, in fact,
我觉得对于我们所有人来说，在整个人生中
we're stronger together.
在一起更强大
FROOME: It goes so much further than running. So much further than sport.
FROOME: 这已经远超于跑步，远超于运动了
It goes to show
这向我们证明
that the preconceived limits that everyone has on everything in life,
每个人都能挑战生命中，生活里的
can be challenged. It's incredible.
每一个极限。非常不可思议
我为人类而跑
我希望能够改变人们的想法
让人们相信人类的潜能是无限的
GRACE KIPCHOGE: That line, "No human is limited,"
GRACE KIPCHOGE: 那句格言，“人类无极限”
I would impart it on any girl.
我会传授给所有女孩
That no matter your gender, no matter where you're born from,
不管你是什么性别，不管你出生在哪里
you are not limited.
没有东西能够的限制你。
You are supposed to actualize your dreams and your passion.
你应该要努力实现自己梦想和抱负
LYNNE KIPCHOGE: It means that you should always work hard,
LYNNE KIPCHOGE: 你需要非常的努力，
no matter what.
面对一切
Not listening to negativity, but listening to positive minds.
不受消极所影响，倾听积极的声音
NDUHIU: In most circumstances, you and me limit ourselves.
NDUHIU：大多情况下，你我受限于自己的认知
It is not other people who limit us. It is us who limit ourselves.
不是前人束缚了我们，而是我们自己甘于止步于此
And I do believe the moment we get over that hurdle,
当我们克服了这些障碍时刻，我相信
then you have the whole world outside there open for you to conquer.
你将更加勇敢且坦然的面对这个世界
你知道，我们都是人类
我们尝试着告诉他们，他们也是可以做到的
SANG: I think the concept is spreading in all sectors of our society.
SANG：我想这个理念已在我们的家乡迅速传播
It is a momentum that is, to me, positive.
对我来说，这是一种前进的动力
You meet teachers from different schools that, when preparing students,
你能看到不同学校的老师们在教导学生时
they are quoting the "No human is limited" story.
会引用"人类无极限"这个故事
And we can see lives being changed.
神奇的变化发生了
[CHEERING]
乔爷冲啊。
COMMENTATOR: I don't know about you guys, but my heart,
解说大哥：不知道你们怎么样，反正我的心，
I can feel it pounding in my shirt this morning.
我明显感觉到我的心都要跳出来了
[CHEERING]
鸡皮疙瘩出来啦
It's 500 meters to go, he is almost there.
500米，他即将冲线
He has one hand on history here in Vienna.
将在维也纳书写历史的时刻
BRAILSFORD: There was an agreement, that if he felt good,
BRAILSFORD：事前我们达成共识，如果他感觉良好
he was gonna tell Valentijn and the other guys would peel off.
他将会告诉Valentijn让其他小伙伴先去领盒饭（散开）
And, sure enough, Valentijn gets the nod and they pulled off. Oh!
看得出，Valentjin点头示意发盒饭，哦！（破风队散开了）
What a wonderful moment!
这个时刻真是太美妙了！
What an absolutely brilliant moment.
真是个美妙绝伦的时刻！
COMMENTATOR: Three hundred meters to go, let's bring him home.
解说：最后300米，来吧，乔爷
He's pointing. "Come on!" he says.
他举起了手，激动的喊出 "掂档！"
Eliud Kipchoge has the hand of history on his shoulder.
乔爷又一次刷新了自己创造的记录（创造了历史上的一刻）
Neil Armstrong we had on the moon in 1969.
尼尔 阿姆斯特丹在1969登上月球
We had Roger Bannister and the four-minute mile 65 years ago.
65年前，罗杰 班尼斯特突破了4分钟的一英里记录
Edmund Hillary, the first man to climb Everest, in 1953.
埃德蒙 希拉里在1953年首登珠峰
Eliud Kipchoge is on his way here.
Eliud Kipchoge 正在步入他们的行列
当我指着自己眼睛的时候
我在告诉这个世界
请用你们自己的双眼见证
2019年10月12日
是创造历史的日子
我希望在全世界人们的心里、血脉里留下一条信息
无论你是跑者、律师 ，老师、工程师
我要对世上的所有人说
人类的潜能是无限的
我已经持有了一个世界记录
2小时1分39秒
但我希望能够创造历史
去鼓舞全人类
这比一个世界记录重要多了
现在，我做到了
BRAILSFORD: It's overwhelming, you know It's a big deal.
BRAILSFORD：势不可挡，你知道吗？这是真的大件事！
People talk about these things, they look at it.
大家都在谈论此事，都在关注着
"A guy ran a marathon."
有个家伙，跑了一场马拉松
He's the first bloke ever, ever in the human race,
他是第一个创造壮举的人
in human history, to do that.
在人类历史上，
And you think, "Oh, God."
你会觉得："天啊！"
And in a crazy little way you've supported that, you know
而且你还以些许疯狂的方式，支持过这个创举
And it means a lot. It means a lot to a lot of people.
此事意义非凡，对大众影响深远
It means a lot to me.
它也将一直影响着我
2019年10月12日， 12万粉丝站在维也纳的街头，见证基普乔格创造了历史
以直播的形式传递到196个国家约5亿个家庭
“人类在耐力、突破极限的能力上的杰出例子”-奥巴马